<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An anatomy of Lievt. Col. John Lilburn's spirit and pamphlets. Or, A vindication of these two honorable patriots Oliver Cromwel, Ld Governor of Ireland, and Sir Arthur Haslerig, Knight baronet, from the unworthy and false aspersions by him cast on them in two libels; the one intituled, An impeachment of high treason against Oliver Cromwel, &amp;c. The other, A preparative to a hue and cry against Sir Arthur Haslerig: wherein the said Lilburn is demonstratively proved to be a common lyar, and unworthy of civil converse.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E575_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864051</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864051</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E575[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An anatomy of Lievt. Col. John Lilburn's spirit and pamphlets. Or, A vindication of these two honorable patriots Oliver Cromwel, Ld Governor of Ireland, and Sir Arthur Haslerig, Knight baronet, from the unworthy and false aspersions by him cast on them in two libels; the one intituled, An impeachment of high treason against Oliver Cromwel, &amp;c. The other, A preparative to a hue and cry against Sir Arthur Haslerig: wherein the said Lilburn is demonstratively proved to be a common lyar, and unworthy of civil converse.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
                  <author>T. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop at the three Daggers neer the Inner-Temple, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cuthbert Sydenham.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.M.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "An impeachment of high treason against Oliver Cromwel" and "A preparative to an hue and cry after Sir Arthur Haslerig", both by John Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 26th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657. --  Preparative to an hue and cry after Sir Arthur Haslerig.</term>
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657. --  Impeachment of high treason against Oliver Cromwel, and his son in law Henry Ireton Esquires, late Members of the late forcibly dissolved House of Commons, presented to publique view.</term>
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hesilrige, Arthur, --  Sir, d. 1661 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165445:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANATOMY OF Lievt. Col. <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN'S</hi> SPIRIT and PAMPHLETS.</p>
            <p>OR, A VINDICATION Of theſe Two Honorable PATRIOTS <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Governor of <hi>Ireland,</hi> AND Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Knight Baronet, FROM THE Unworthy and falſe Aſperſions by him caſt on them in two LIBELS; The one intituled, <hi>An Jmpeachment of High Treaſon against OLIVER CROMWEL, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Other, <hi>A Preparative to a Hue and Cry against Sir ARTH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R HASLERIG:</hi> Wherein the ſaid LILBURN is demonſtrative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved to be a common Lyar, and unworthy of civil Converſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 10.31.</hi>
               </bibl> The mouth of the juſt bringeth forth wiſdom: but the froward tongue ſhall be cut out.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 4.16.</hi>
               </bibl> They ſleep not, except they have done miſchief; and their ſleep is taken away, except they have cauſed ſome to fall.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude,</hi> verſ. <hi>9.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord rebuke thee.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the three Daggers neer the <hi>Inner-Temple, Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165445:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165445:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Houſe of Commons THE Supream Authority OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Senators,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Need not make my Apology, if I dedicate this little Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to You, becauſe it moſt concerns You, not onely for that the Diſhonor of Your own Members reflects on You all, but alſo for that You are firſt ſtruck at, and theſe are but ſparks of that fire, that have been firſt kindled (if poſſible) to conſume You. As I have with much joy and admiration, in my ſolitary and private converſation, viewed the
<pb facs="tcp:165445:3"/> eminent actings of providences among You; ſo I have, with almoſt as much lamentation and wonder, bewailed the unhandſom and unſuitable deportments of mens ſpirits and actions, oppoſing of You; But moſt of all the exceeding boldneſs and impudency, together with the tranſcendent rage and venom of that generation of men which are truly called LEVELLERS, a Faction grown out of Your own Bowels, whom I know not what to call, but the putrifaction of GOD'S Mercies and Your Indulgencies, whoſe Principles, as they are begotten by the corruptions of Perſons and Governments, ſo they are maintained and onely thrive by Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and Confuſions; a People who have as many Governments as Religions, and as little of the true Religion, as they have of Eſtates and Fortunes in this Nation; men of no more reputation, then what they get among diſcontented and bank-rooted perſons, by holding forth taking and ſeeming Propoſitions of Levelling and Licentiouſneſs: And yet theſe men are ſuffered <hi>(in perpetuum noſtri ſeculi infamium)</hi> to ſcandalize Your <hi>Supream Authority,</hi> to raiſe Mutinies and Tumults againſt You, to ſlander Your moſt publique and active Inſtruments, and tolerated, yea, by many countenanced, as if they were the moſt uſeful Inſtruments, or had ſome myſterious glory in their Perſons and Pamphlets, that it were Blasphemy for any ſober man to ſpeak againſt. But, among all this popular and ſeditious Gange, there is none hath more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored this Nation, and contemned Your Authority, then Lievtenant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> their desperate and wretched Inſtrument, who thinks he can attain to no higher reputation, then to deny Your <hi>Authority:</hi> He hath called You once and again, <hi>a Junto, Colonel</hi> Prides <hi>Junto, a Mock-Parliament, a company of Theeves, and Murtherers, and Felons;</hi> made publique Libels againſt the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> the <hi>Army, General, Lievtenant General,</hi> all Your Officers; ſlighted all Your Orders, Ordinances, <hi>Acts,</hi> and glories in it to Your very faces; What a Reproach is this to Your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? What a Weakening to Your Cauſe, and Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Your Friends? What an emboldening Your Enemies, that <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> a man of ſuch an inconſiderable Interest, one who could hardly ever challenge more Land in <hi>England</hi> then might Geometrically ſerve to make his grave, ſhould be ſuffered thus publiquely, and upon Record, to defame not onely Your Perſons ſingly, but ſcorn Your very Government and <hi>Authority,</hi> as honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:165445:3"/> men do tyranny and inhumanity, without any ſignal puniſhment to the terror of the reſt? And, if I may ſpeak <hi>vox populi,</hi> the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar think, Your Guilt is the cauſe of Your Patience, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of his Boldneſs: and what <hi>arcanum imperii</hi> there may be in Your breſts, I know not; But You little know, how theſe fooliſh Papers do Gangrene the moſt of men, and according to their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent tempers and affections, have their divers and ominous oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations: The worſer ſort of men rejoyce, and take heart, and feed their Malignant humors and diſcontents by them; The indifferent and moderate ones know not what to ſay, but think enough; The better ſort, and Your Friends, are much diſheartened, and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, and have cauſe to think You are doubtful of Your own <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> ſince You are ſo cold in maintaining it. Pardon me, if I, out of the abundant ſenſe of Your Honors and the Nations Happineſs, be ſomewhat zealous in ſtirring You up to look about You. <hi>England</hi> hath been a ſtage of Glory and divine Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: You have been carryed on, by a wonder of Providence, through many Difficulties, and have been made Inſtruments of gallant actions, among all which, that Act of Juſtice, done by You on the late King, renders You a Glory to This, and a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to all other Nations: And ſhall the Honor of theſe tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (wherein the finger of the Almighty himſelf hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable) be undermined by the diſcontents of a few Mechanick Levellers? or be ſuffered to be blaſted by the puny pen of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted Humorist? What will after ages ſay? What will other Nations think? Either maintain Your Government, or give Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to all men to affront You: It's Equity and Juſtice that ſome ſhould be made Examples to others, now, as others have been made to them heretofore: If You give way to this, You ſhall not want abuſes, and all Your Friends.</p>
            <p>It is the opinion and ſerious judgment of many ſober and wiſe, yea godly men, that bleſs GOD for this Change, and lament the miſeries of the times, that one great occaſion, if it be not a cauſe of this ſort of mens oppoſition to you, flows from that unlimited Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of RELIGION which is yet granted in this Nation, and think that there is ſomewhat divine and judicial in it, that the first fruits of their new Opinions and Principles ſhould be the abuſing your Authority and Government, that you may ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times what the end of ſuch a Toleration will be, and prevent it.
<pb facs="tcp:165445:4"/> For it's moſt obſervable, that as it was the great and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principle in their Agreement of the People, (without which all other civil Grants was nothing,) ſo it may be almoſt mathematically demonſtrated, that all that turn Levellers, first leave the Principles of Scripture-Religion, that they may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out check of conſcience for any civil diſorder. Religion is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bond and tye on mens ſpirits, as well to Civil, as to Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Rules, and when once men forſake theſe Principles, no hearty or cordial obedience can be expected: As Tyrants and Politicians firſt ſtrive to enſlave mens conſciences, and then they are ſure of their perſons; ſo when men mean to level all things to their luſts and humours, they firſt make ſhipwrack of a good conſcience. And it's not to be wondered, that men ſhould deny the common and ordinary Rules of Civil Government, who have profeſſedly denyed all Rules and Inſtitutions both of Law and Gospel; for though Religion and Civil Government be of different natures, yet they are commonly inter-woven together, as to the flouriſhing of each other; that Government ſhall never thrive where Religion is not advanced, nor will Religion much flouriſh in the midst of Factions or Schiſms, or under Popular or Tyrannical Governments of States; yet commonly the one is bleſſed by the other, Gods deſign being to advance himſelf firſt, to ſet up his own Name, and then to prosper Nations.</p>
            <p>I am conſtrained (Honourable Worthies) to repreſent this Conſideration to you, that you would vindicate your own names in advancing Chriſts, and expect no hearty conjunction of any with you, in this Government, but honeſt and conſciencious men, who can only be engaged by Principles of Religion, and Civil Freedom; for men that have left the Principles of the Scripture, the Rule of Religion, expect nothing elſe but they ſhall, as they find their l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st act, ſoon oppoſe the moſt fundamental Maximes you can lay down as a baſis to your Goverment. It is the fear of this unlimited Toleration makes many honeſt Preſbyterians ſtand at ſuch a distance, and ſo unwilling to ſubmit to this change; yea, that makes you loſe many a godly heart, which elſe would rejoyce in former acts done by you, while they ſee no more ſignal Character of favour and reſpect profeſſedly ſet on the Principles of the Gospel, then on Heatheniſm, or Judaiſm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually hear Blasphemies ſpoken <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> at leaſt without
<pb facs="tcp:165445:4"/> puniſhment. Is our Religion ſo uncertain, or doubtful, that it need to have falſe Religions to try it by? Is Blasphemy a leſs ſin then it was? or, is Gods honor faln in its worth and excellency, that it ſhould not be as much preſerved as ever? God forbid. Liberty of Conſcience muſt be given onely to men that can be ſuppoſed conſcienciouſly to differ, not onely from Religion, but ſome externall way of practiſing the ſame Principle. But I leave it to Your wiſe and ſerious Conſideration, onely preſent You with this Vindication of two of Your faithful and active <hi>Agents</hi> of this Nation, You have Power enough to vindicate Your own <hi>Authority;</hi> I can do no more then witneſs againſt the falſe and wicked asperſions of Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> againſt them, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to Your Iudgments, as thoſe who ought to take the prime cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of it, that You may know what Servants You, and this State hath, and what an evil and intolerable perſon this <hi>John Lilburn</hi> is to live under the favor and ſmiling aspect of ſuch a State, or, which he makes the onely Butt of his madneſs and malice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt humble Servant, <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165445:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165445:5"/>
            <head>AN ANATOMY OF Lievt. Colonel <hi>John Lilburn's</hi> SPIRIT and PAMPHLETS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the Exorbitancies of this laſt age, there is none hath ſtained the Glory of this Nation more then the multitude of licentious and abuſive Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets that continually fly abroad like Atomes in the Air, whereby the Preſs is made a common Strumpet to conceive and bring forth the froth of every idle and wanton fancy, or to vent the malice and venom of every diſcontented and debaucht ſpirit: and Books, that were wont to be monuments of the induſtry and ſeriouſneſs of mens ſpirits, and records of the vertues and noble acts of brave men, adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Reaſon and Judgment, and ordained to be as embalmings to their names, are now turned into Paſquils and Libels, ſtuft with the rancor and rage of theſe men, who know no way to recruit their own loſt reputation, but by defacing the names of their betters. But of all the Pamphlets that I have yet ſeen, there are none that expreſs ſuch a dangerous and unworthy ſpirit, as thoſe that go under the name of Lievt. Colonel <hi>John Lilburn.</hi> Some Pamphlets, though they have little of truth, yet have nothing of falſhood: Others, though of little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165445:6"/> yet may ſerve to divert a ſtudious head from the continual preſſures of more ſerious thoughts. Others are pretty eſſays, and done on purpoſe to engage better pens in manifeſting Truth; and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual writing, or rather ſcribling of the moſt, demonſtrates that men are not idle, but that the Nation is big with ſomething that will be brought forth at laſt in form and beauty. In <hi>Diurnals</hi> (thoſe lean and miſerable ſheets) you have ſome things true, among many miſtakes, and lyes but probably reported; and you may know how the days paſs away by them, though there be little elſe. In <hi>Pragmaticus</hi> and <hi>the Man in the Moon,</hi> with the reſt of that bauling Crue, you have ſome wit, with their malice; But this man (eſpecially in his two laſt Pamphlets) breaking all the bonds of Religion, Civility, Humanity, profeſſing open defiance to the Laws of Grace and Nature,) hath devoted himſelf to ſlander, reproach, defame, rack, and crucifie the names of all ſorts of men that have the face of honeſty, or that cannot comply with him in his Levelling Deſigns; ſwelling up his Title-pages with horrid and naſty expreſſions, as <hi>Polecat, Foxes, Wolves,</hi> and ſuch like, as if he had been newly come out of the Deſarts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> or been converſing with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſeven years at graſs, interlining his ſentences with barbarous and cruel Invectives againſt men in Authority, calling them <hi>Murtherers, Theeves, Robbers,</hi> threatning them with the <hi>worſt of deaths;</hi> quoting himſelf and his own Pamphlets as often as others do the moſt learned and orthodox Authors, with ſuch like expreſſions as theſe, <hi>P.</hi> 2. <hi>See to this purpoſe my Impeachment of High Treaſon, &amp;c. See my Arguments or Reaſons in the ſecond Edition of my Book of the</hi> 8. <hi>of June,</hi> 1649. <hi>intituled, The Legal and Fundamental Liberties of England, &amp;c. P.</hi> 3. <hi>Peruſe carefully, I entreat you, the</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>pages of my Impeachment, &amp;c. as alſo the</hi> 12. <hi>and</hi> 16. <hi>pages of the ſecond Edition of my forementioned Book. So P.</hi> 4. <hi>See my ſecond Edition of my Picture of the Councel of State.</hi> Making bold and daring Titles, that men may expect great things from; and when they are engaged to look after the proofs, finde nothing but a heap of Impertinencies, and a Catalogue of his Petitions, and Letters, and Conferences, and Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to his other Pamphlets for ſatisfaction; but <hi>ſatis eſt repetere.</hi> He that loves the ſmell, may have enough of theſe noiſom weeds almoſt in every line or ſentence. As for ſober and ſerious men, I know their ſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acks riſe at firſt ſight: But my intent, in this Diſcourſe, is not to run through all his Volumes, by which he hath defiled the Preſs, and brought himſelf into a labyrinth of juſt Troubles and Miſeries, leſt, in raking
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165445:6"/> ſuch a Dunghil, I ſhould raiſe too great a ſtink in the noſtrils of my ſelf and Reader; I ſhall follow his own requeſt, and refer it to any, who have patience enough, and are not ſubject to fall into the ſame diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, unto the peruſing of them: But ſhall view him in his laſt works, which ſhould be his beſt and moſt ſolemn manifeſtations of himſelf, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing he thinks he is ſo nigh his death.</p>
            <p>I have read, of late, two Pamphlets under his name and authority, and by them you may probably gueſs of the reſt; The Title of the firſt being <hi>An Impeachment of High Treaſon againſt Mr OLIVER CROMWEL and his Son in Law HENRY IRETON,</hi> (for ſo he is pleaſed to ſtile them;) and the laſt <hi>A Preparative to a Hue and Cry againſt Sir ARTH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R HASLERIG:</hi> At the reading of the Titles I was much amazed, the accuſations being ſo high, and affirmations ſo poſitive, and the language ſo terrible, that I began to reflect on the Gentlemen with ſtrange apprehenſions, and to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſuch men ſhould live, and be ſo much in the eyes of honeſt men, and yet be guilty of ſuch Crimes, that all the Villains and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in this Nation never equalled them; and was impatient to be in the midſt of his Pamphlets, to hear their Charge, expecting the Titles to be but a ſhadow and a name onely to that ſubſtance of proof I ſhould finde againſt them; not dreaming that any man could be ſo impudent, and carry ſuch a face of braſs and wickedneſs, as to abuſe not onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but himſelf ſo demonſtratively, if he had not much againſt them, and that by the evidence of noon day: But, contrary to all this, when I looked for to have ſeen the horrible Crimes written with a Sun beam, and terrifying my ſpirit at the firſt appearance, I could finde little elſe but the Copies of <hi>Letters and Petitions,</hi> empty and fooliſh gloryings in himſelf, railing upon other men, and the whole <hi>Parliament</hi> equal with them, which made me much more to wonder what was become of the Religion, Conſcience, Modeſty, and Sobriety of the man; and to conclude, that certainly he was either drunk, or in a dream, when he writ theſe ſheets.</p>
            <p>But, that all honeſt men may know him for the future, I ſhall take ſo much pains as to conſider his Charge againſt theſe two Gentlemen, <hi>viz.</hi> againſt Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> now Lord Governor of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> now Governor of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> on <hi>Tine,</hi> men of ſuch integrity and honor, that <hi>John Lilburn</hi> could not pitch on two leſs capable of his malice and reproach then they, and that (though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will) his calumnies will be but foils to ſet off their honeſty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165445:7"/> and innocency with greater grace to all ingenuous and ſober men.</p>
            <p>To his <hi>Impeachment of High Treaſon</hi> (of Mr <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> as he calls him,) the firſt queſtion, by any man that reads the Charge, wil be, <hi>Where are the Articles?</hi> I have looked over the Pamphlet with as much diligence and obſervance as his method would permit me, and I finde not one diſtinct Article of any miſdemeanors that hath the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Charge, much leſs of High Treaſon, and the Higheſt Treaſon, but onely a Letter to Mr <hi>Holland,</hi> and a Challenge, and a Prayer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he abuſeth the bleſſed Name of the moſt High God, and invocates him to deſtroy and root out the name of <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his poſterity, with ſuch hideous imprecations, that any Chriſtian tongue would fail and ſtammer but to repeat, much leſs to urge to God as a Prayer; and ſome looſe expreſſions about <hi>Cromwels</hi> complying with the King, and his ſhedding the blood of War in the time of Peace: but it may be this he intended as the Charge, for which he calls him <hi>a Murtherer and a Traytor,</hi> and ſays, <hi>He deſerves to dye rather then the late King, or, then all the Judges and Villains that have been condemned ever ſince the Conqueſt:</hi> And if his meaning be ſo, (for there is nothing elſe that looks like it) let the World be judg of the Treaſon.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>His compliance with the late King,</hi> I ſhall ſay no more to it but this;</p>
            <p>Firſt, If there were any ſuch compliance or engagement, doubtleſs the King would have made advantage enough of it, eſpecially would have manifeſted ſomething of it to the world, or given ſome hint of it that might have reflected on <hi>Cromwel,</hi> while he lived; and moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when he ſaw what was like to be done with him by the Power of the <hi>Parliament and Army:</hi> But the King neither by word, nor in that Book which goes under his name, doth give an intimation of any ſuch compliance: And ſecondly, He hath manifeſted the contrary by his practiſe and conſtant oppoſition to him, and his party, ever ſince; and of late, by his ſtrenuous endeavors to bring him to Juſtice; by which all honeſt men may well be ſatisfied, that it was but a ſlander, and a whelp of <hi>John Lilburns</hi> malice.</p>
            <p>Were <hi>John Lilburns</hi> compliance with Malignants in the Tower, and other where, printed, we ſhould ſoon have cauſe to ſequeſter him from his 3000 <hi>l.</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham:</hi> It's well known, beſides his trading in <hi>Cooks Inſtitutes,</hi> what Malignant converſe he &amp; Judg <hi>Jenkins</hi> have had together, ſome fruits of it we ſee in his Pamphlets, but I will not impeach him; you ſee, Reader, what his firſt Article amounts unto.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165445:7"/>
            <p>His ſecond Charge, whereby he calls him a wilful murtherer, is, <hi>For that he, about the</hi> 15 <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1647. <hi>near</hi> Ware <hi>in</hi> Hartford-ſhire, <hi>wilfully and of ſet malice murthered</hi> Rich. Arnell, <hi>and ſo ſhed the blood of War in the time of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That you may ſee the malice of this man, and his unexpreſſible rage, he taxeth <hi>Cromwel</hi> with that which was done by the whole Councel of War, and by the General, rather then by him, who was but a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and had only a ſingle vote; and he might rather ſay, that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Councel of War murthered him, then of Lieutenant General <hi>Cromwel;</hi> yea, he may as well ſay, That it's murther to ſhoot a Souldier to death for any Mutiny or enormious crime whatever, as for that; and whereas he thinks to make up his Treaſon by this expreſſion, <hi>That it was the blood of War in the time of Peace.</hi> Can he call it a time of Peace, when an Enemy is but newly ſubdued, and an Army kept up, and an Enemy feared? However (that he may have his deſire) grant it to be a time of Peace, that is, that no viſible Enemy appears; yet doth not he deſerve to dye that ſhall begin a new War in a time of Peace? And ſhall, when there is no common Enemy, raiſe a Mutiny among the Souldiers, which is the firſt principle of a War? Nay, is not he rather to be adjudged to death, that, when an Army hath conquered a common Enemy, will begin a new War among themſelves? This is <hi>Richard Arnels</hi> cauſe, who was a Ring-leader in that firſt Mutiny, which was the firſt diſcovery of the levelling Agitators, and their wicked intentions; and had <hi>John Lilburn</hi> his due (who was then coming to the Army, but durſt not appear among them) he had not had the opportunity to have burthened the world with his ſcandalous Libels, as now he hath. Thus you have <hi>John Lilburns</hi> Impeachment, and theſe his horrid crimes of Treaſon, for which Lieut. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> deſerves to dye ſo many thouſand deaths, according to his Law: Can any man believe, this man ever conſulted ſo much as with his <hi>ſenſus communis,</hi> much leſs either with God or Nature, when he writ this Pamphlet? Or that ever he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed his expreſſions after they dropt from the fury of his ſpirit? Or can any man imagine, that this man is not more fit for <hi>Bedlam,</hi> then for the drawing up fundamental Principles of Government? But I pity him, for certainly he never thought any man of underſtanding or ſeriouſneſs would ever read his Pamphlets: It hath been a juſt judgment of God on him, ſince he left off converſing with the Principles of Religion, to let an unclean ſpirit poſſeſs him, wherby, that he might follow the devils art ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, he hath ever oppoſed thoſe, &amp; delighted to caſt dirt in the faces of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165445:8"/> thoſe that have been moſt publique Inſtruments, and God from heaven hath moſt honoured to do ſervice to his people. But I have done with his Impeachment, and only add this, The Gentleman who he thus ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, hath that character of reſpect in the hearts of all that love the good of this Nation, that no ſuch <hi>Momus</hi> can deface by the blackeſt ſlanders he can lay on him. For me to make <hi>encomiums</hi> of his vertues and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts from this Nation, were but to ſet paint on burniſht marble, he is now gone to do more work in another Nation, and may he do as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and gallant ſervice there as he hath done in <hi>England,</hi> while <hi>John Lilburn</hi> ſwells up himſelf in rage and malice, vomits nothing but Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Murther againſt him, and other true-hearted Engliſhmen.</p>
            <p>I am now come to his preparative to a Hue and Cry after Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig,</hi> (for the Gentleman you ſee is big with more wrath,) and becauſe <hi>Cromwel</hi> is gone, and he cannot follow him to <hi>Ireland,</hi> that he may not be out of action, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> muſt be the next ſubject of his envy and wrath, as if railing and lying were his element; he is ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to it, that he is reſolved to hazard his very life in the acting of it. I dare not repeat his Title, with all the expreſſions of it, leſt I trouble the Reader again with the ill ſavour of them, he that reads them, would think Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had been a monſter, and no man, that he was not fit to breathe in a common air. But that now at laſt the world may ſee what a man of diſcontent and unhappineſs this <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> is, before the end of the ſtory, you ſhall find him a perfect Lyar, one that cares not what he ſays, ſo he may ſay ſomething to diſgrace.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I have had but little perſonal acquaintance with Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> (or with the other Gentleman) and know not what inviſible and particular infirmities, common to mankind, he may labour under: I am not of that opinion, but that the beſt of men have their <hi>Errata's,</hi> as well as Lieut. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for his publique tranſactions in the North, I have followed this Hue and Cry throughout the four Northern Counties, the publique ſtage of his actions, and find his name exceeding precious among honeſt men, and I can ſay with the vote of all but Malignants (unto whom he hath been a juſt terror) that they bleſs God that ever he came to the North, and do think it was as ſeaſonable and prudential an act to ſend him to be Governor of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> as any act of a like nature done by the Parliament, and could heartily wiſh every Gariſon had ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, and every Regiment ſuch a Colonel: But <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> as if he were the Epitome of all Freedom and Liberty, the Centre of all Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165445:8"/> the publique and great perſon againſt whom onely <hi>Treaſon and Murther</hi> can be committed, <hi>Preſidium, &amp; dulce decus,</hi> the ſafeguard and glory of the <hi>Nation,</hi> complains, and cries out on Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> for but a common, an ordinary act (which yet is moſt falſly reported) as <hi>a Felon, a Murtherer, &amp;c.</hi> though all the <hi>North</hi> rejoyce, and bleſs God for his preſence, and honeſty.</p>
            <p>But his diligence and induſtry, his vigilance and intereſt the laſt year, when the <hi>Scots</hi> came in, may well be printed as one great cauſe of the <hi>Preſervation of the North,</hi> notwithſtanding his brother <hi>Henry Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> at the ſame time, betrayed <hi>Tinmouth</hi> Caſtle: His fair and equal carriage and reſpect to all honeſt men, though of ſeveral judgments, his diſcountenancing <hi>Malignants,</hi> his ſevere and careful improvement of <hi>Sequeſtrations</hi> for the uſe of <hi>the State,</hi> make his name more precious to honeſt men, then all, or any, or a thouſand like expreſſions can to render it unſavory.</p>
            <p>But let us follow the <hi>Hue and Cry,</hi> and ſee more particularly what the man ſtorms ſo much for: The Reader may ſee that the ground of this <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> is a <hi>Letter</hi> written from <hi>George Lilburn,</hi> whom he calls <hi>Eſquire,</hi> that the World may beleeve he hath a Gentleman to his Uncle, though it's well known, before theſe times, he never had the birth, breeding, nor eſtate of a Gentleman; his carriage in the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſervice</hi> will be ſhortly diſcovered, that if you conſider but the <hi>Letter à quo,</hi> and the <hi>Letter ad quem,</hi> you will be pretty well ſatisfied of the ground of the <hi>Pamphlet;</hi> a ſuſpected and guilty Uncle writes to a diſcontented and malicious Nephew, and between them both they bring forth a Monſter called <hi>A Hue and Cry:</hi> The Uncle is under exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and like to have ſtrange things proved againſt him, <hi>viz. That he hath been a Malignant formerly, and ſince he hath profest to be a Parliamenteer, hath cheated the State:</hi> And hath now no way left him to make the world beleeve he is honeſt, but by defaming Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur,</hi> before whom moſt of his Knaveries are already, and are to be heard: And no fitter Inſtrument for to do it, but <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> a man of a deſperate and loſt fortune: Two things he lays to Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> Charge, as heinous and unpardonable Crimes; Firſt, <hi>That he hath Feloniouſly robbed him of between twenty four and twenty five hundred pounds.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That he hath brib'd falſe witneſſes to take away his life.</hi> For proof of the firſt, <hi>page</hi> 3. he ſaith, <hi>He cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon what pretence Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerig <hi>and Colonel</hi> George Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, <hi>and the reſt of the Committee at</hi> Newcaſtle, <hi>can ſeize upon his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165445:9"/> Estate in the hands of Sir</hi> Henry Bellingham <hi>and</hi> Thomas Bowes, <hi>and ſtop his Rents due from Sir</hi> Henry Gibb <hi>his hands, to the full value of betwixt twenty four and twenty five hundred pounds:</hi> So that it is moſt apparent by his own exprrſſion, That if any thing was done, it was not by Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> alone, but by <hi>the whole Committee:</hi> He ſaith, <hi>That they have ſtopped Rents, due to him from Sir</hi> Hen: Gibb <hi>his hands, to the value of about twenty four or twenty five hundred pounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to that, the <hi>Order of Parliament</hi> commanded, <hi>That all Delinquents Rents, not excepted from Pardon, and Papiſts, ſhould be ſtayed in the Tenants hands till the firſt of September laſt;</hi> and this <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Lilburns</hi> bears date the 18. of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> So that then both <hi>Bellinghams, Bowes,</hi> and <hi>Gibbs</hi> Rents were all ſtayd by <hi>Authority of Parliament,</hi> and not by Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> arbitrary tyrannical will and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; But to obey <hi>Orders of Parliament</hi> is <hi>Felony</hi> in <hi>John Lilburns</hi> Law: And for <hi>Lilburns</hi> eſtate, ſeized by Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> in the hands of Sir <hi>Henry Bellingham</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> they have both made their Compoſitions; the Moyety of <hi>Bowes</hi> Fine came to Two hundred pounds, which was payd into the Treaſury; the Moyety of Sir <hi>Henry Bellinghams</hi> Compoſition, for his Lands in <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> (which did onely concern <hi>John Lilburn</hi>) was about One pound; and his chief Eſtate being in <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> Mr <hi>Richard Lilburn,</hi> Father to <hi>John,</hi> and one of the <hi>Committee,</hi> gave his free conſent, and was very well contented, that the <hi>Committee of Westmerland</hi> ſhould receive that firſt Moyety due to his Son <hi>John,</hi> and that Sir <hi>Henry Bellingham</hi> ſhould pay the Moyety of his whole Fine to the <hi>Committee of Weſtmerland,</hi> for the ſpeedy disbanding of their Horſe; So that there was but onely <hi>Thomas Bowes</hi> Two hundred pounds, either of Rent or Compoſition-money, due to <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> that came into the Treaſury; and Mr <hi>Richard Lilburn</hi> complaining to the <hi>Committee</hi> of his Sons great wants, and neceſſities, and deſiring maintenance for him, being in priſon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating his ſad affliction by the ſickneſs of his Wife, and death of ſome of his Children, and infection amongſt the reſt, the <hi>Committee</hi> gave an Order to his Father for the receiving of that Two hundred pounds, which accordingly was payd him, and no doubt <hi>John Lilburn</hi> received it long ſince, the <hi>Order</hi> being granted before his <hi>Letter</hi> bears date: And thus you ſee, not one penny, either of Rents or Compoſition-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys belonging to <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> was before the 18. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Treaſury, neither is there, as yet, one penny of his money payd in; Let all honeſt men therefore judg whether Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> has
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165445:9"/> robbed <hi>John Lilburn</hi> of between Twenty four and Twenty five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, and whether Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> deſerves, or, as <hi>John Lilburn</hi> prints, <hi>may, or ought, to be knocked in the head, as a Polecat, Fox, Wolf.</hi> What humor and deſperate fury poſſeſt the man that he thus foams out his own ſhame? You ſee he hath perfectly learnt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavils</hi> great Principle of wickedneſs, <hi>Calumniare audacter aliquid haerebit;</hi> Slander to purpoſe, ſomething will ſtick: But enough of that.</p>
            <p>For the proofs of <hi>Lilburns</hi> ſecond Charge of Sir <hi>Arthur, bribing falſe witneſſes to take away his life, and to murther him,</hi> it is in <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>becauſe he was one of his unjuſt Judges that, for nothing, committed him:</hi> This needs no large Anſwer; It is notoriouſly known the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> committed him for <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and his Pamphlets do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declare their grounds; and ſurely ſuch ſtuff was never written and publiſhed againſt any <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Supream Authority</hi> of any Nation, and the Author moſt audaciouſly to juſtifie it.</p>
            <p>For his ſecond proof he prints a ſtory of one <hi>William Blank,</hi> this <hi>William Blank,</hi> about the 13. of <hi>April</hi> laſt, came to the door, where the <hi>Councel of State</hi> then ſate, and delivered a Paper to Mr <hi>Froſt</hi> the Secretary, wherein he informed, <hi>That one Sir</hi> Peter Rocket <hi>a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was in</hi> London, <hi>and contriving a moſt dangerous Deſign againſt the Publique, and that the ſaid Sir</hi> Peter Rocket <hi>had been in</hi> London <hi>the year before, ſtirring up the Citizens to riſe in arms about the time of the ſiege at</hi> Colcheſter, <hi>and that divers Citizens and Apprentices were combined with him.</hi> After the Information was read, the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State</hi> appointed Lievt. General <hi>Cromwel</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> to ſpeak with <hi>Blank,</hi> from time to time, for diſcovery of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and before that day Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> never ſaw him, nor heard of him: <hi>Blank</hi> thereupon went to the Lievt. Generals houſe, and finding his employments ſo great that he could not often ſpeak with him, went to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> and told him, that two of Mr <hi>Ruſhworths,</hi> the Lord Generals Secretaries ſervants were in the Plot againſt the <hi>State,</hi> and named divers Merchants of quality in the City, and told of their Meetings, Debates and Reſolutions in ſeveral places, both in City and Country, and that himſelf was preſent at their Meetings, and heard their Debates, and ſaw ſuch &amp; ſuch men at thoſe Meetings, and at laſt, that the Reſolution was the ſurprizing <hi>the General,</hi> the taking of the <hi>Preſident of the Councel of State,</hi> the <hi>Speaker of the Parliament,</hi> L. Gen. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> &amp; divers of the chief Officers of the Army, and to deſtroy them and others; And that this way was carryed on by a <hi>Committee,</hi> half of <hi>John
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165445:10"/> Lilburns party,</hi> and half of <hi>the Kings party,</hi> and that they were all under an <hi>engagement by oath,</hi> and named ſome members of one Mr <hi>Lambs</hi> Church, and then told the appointed day when it ſhould be put in execution, which was about the 24 of <hi>April: Blank</hi> ſpoke not a word to Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> but he made him to ſet it down with his own hand, and put his name to it, and kept a <hi>Diary</hi> of all his Informations, from the time he came firſt to the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> to the 24. of <hi>April,</hi> the time when the Plot ſhould have been acted; and <hi>Blank</hi> gave the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why that 24. day ſhould be the day, becauſe that then ſuch Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers were to be both at the Lord Generals houſe, and upon the Guards, as were privy to the Deſigns: Then Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> with the advice of the Lievt. General, acquainted Commiſſary General <hi>Ireton</hi> with it, the day growing very neer when the Plot ſhould be effected; and that very night, as <hi>Blank</hi> informed, the <hi>Malignants</hi> ſhould riſe upon the <hi>winding of a Horn.</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> carryed <hi>Blank</hi> to Commiſſary General <hi>Ireton</hi> at S. <hi>James's,</hi> and He, and Colonel <hi>Pride,</hi> and ſome other Officers, marvelling at <hi>Blanks</hi> confident ſpeeches concerning the Deſign, and examining him in all his Papers, he affirming that theſe things were true, they preſently apprehended two of Mr <hi>Ruſhworths</hi> Servants, and they were brought to S. <hi>James's</hi> face to face before <hi>Blank,</hi> they denyed their ever ſeeing him, or being at any ſuch place as he mentioned, and he affirmed, and they denyed; Commiſſary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Ireton</hi> and Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> then took care of the chief Officers of the Guard, and ſent ſome Officers with <hi>Blank</hi> to apprehend ſome of the Citizens, <hi>viz. George Almoner, William Seubal, John Arrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, James, Eddington,</hi> whom they found in their houſes, and in bed; and they brought them about one a clock in the night to S. <hi>Iames</hi>'s: when they came, it appeared they were the <hi>Parliaments</hi> very good friends, and all the Informations that <hi>Blank</hi> had given, were all falſe, and had not the leaſt colour or ſhadow of truth in them; and <hi>Blank</hi> did before their faces acknowledg, that what he had ſet under his hand was falſe, and that he had never ſeen them at any ſuch Meetings: The Gentlemen having ſeen the Reaſon, why they were ſent for, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Blank was a very naughty young fellow, and they knew both him and his Father,</hi> returned to their houſes, and the Commiſſary General and Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> kept <hi>Blank</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Eddington,</hi> which <hi>Blank</hi> ſaid was Sir <hi>Peter Rockets</hi> Servant, for a further diſcovery of the truth: Then it being between two or three in the morning, Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> went from S. <hi>James's</hi> to his Lodging, and never ſince that time ever ſaw <hi>Blank,</hi> or heard from him; neither did he, at
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165445:10"/> any time, give him any money, or promiſe of money; But about two or three days after, ſpeaking with the Commiſſary General, he told Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> that what ever <hi>Blank</hi> had ſaid or written, were lyes, and that <hi>Blank</hi> was adjudged to run the Gantlope, and ſurely if he were not well whipt, the Souldiers deſerve to be blamed; and whereas <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſays, <hi>he was no Souldier,</hi> it will be affirmed on Oath, that <hi>Blank</hi> confeſt to an Officer of the Army, that he was of Col. <hi>Hortons</hi> Regiment of Horſe, and that of the Colonels own Troop, and that his horſe ſtood at <hi>Sawpots</hi> the Kings-head in <hi>Grays-in-lane,</hi> and deſired a Certificate to Col: <hi>Horton</hi> to excuſe his abſence from the Troop: Then Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> hearing that after he had run the Gantlope, he went to the Tower to <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> and thereupon <hi>Lilburn</hi> began to blazon theſe falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that he hath ſince printed. Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> being to go into the <hi>North,</hi> delivered all <hi>Blanks</hi> Informations, with his own hand, and ſigned with his own name, to Mr <hi>Iohn Price</hi> at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> entreating him to publiſh the truth of that ſtory, if need required: And thus you ſee how guilty Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> is of murther, in conſpiring to take away his life; but the man hath got <hi>Cains</hi> ſpirit, and is afraid that every man that ſees him will deſtroy him; ſee what it is to have a <hi>guilty conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his fear yet encreaſes, and <hi>page</hi> 9. relates a long ſtory of one <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Varney,</hi> which Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> imployed to entrap him, and ſo to take away his life.</p>
            <p>As for this <hi>Varney</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> verily thinks he never ſaw him, unleſs it ſhould be one <hi>Varney</hi> that was ſon to the Marſhal that was killed at <hi>Edg-hill,</hi> that was a Trooper under him, and ran to the Enemy when he was in the Weſt; if that be the man, he hath not ſeen him, nor ſpoke with him, nor heard from him this five or ſix years; if it be not the man, he knows neither firſt nor laſt any thing of him, nor the deſign, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaw it in <hi>Lilburns</hi> Pamphlet. <hi>Parturiunt montes;</hi> What is become of all theſe high and great expreſſions? Do not you think, <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> that Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> is a man not fit for humane ſociety, that he deſerves death more then the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and may be knocked in the head, like a <hi>Polecat?</hi> &amp;c. I need make no Application.</p>
            <p>There is one additional Charge yet which I will but name, that is, <hi>That Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>was none of the Committee,</hi> and his Uncle <hi>George</hi> thinks the ſame, whereas Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> was authorized by the <hi>Parliament</hi> to ſit in all <hi>Commiſſions</hi> and <hi>Committees</hi> in the four <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Counties,</hi> and it's happy for the Biſhoprick he is one, elſe his Uncle would play as mad pranks there as <hi>Iohn</hi> doth above.</p>
            <p>You now ſee, <hi>Reader,</hi> the picture of <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> what a fair and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165445:11"/> lovely aſpect he caſts upon honeſt men, what a precious ſavour flows from his Pen, how worthy this man is to live among humane ſociety, or to model <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> that makes no conſcience of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, ſcandalizing, lying; what deſperate and dangerous principles he acts upon, holding private murther, in revenge, to be lawful, eſteeming the life of an honeſt man, if but diſſenting from him, or doing him any particular wrong, to be no more then the life of a beaſt of prey; and if theſe be his ſerious thoughts in cold blood (if you can imagine him to be at any time in a cool &amp; ſober temper) what may he not attempt to do in his raging raptures? It maybe very probably expected, that he which hath given ſuch a licence to his Pen to vent his malice, may let looſe his hands to do ſome ſuch horrible act as private, and wilful murther, that he may confirm by his practiſe what he entertains as his principle; and it's juſt with God that theſe which make lyes their refuge, ſhould make deſtruction their end.</p>
            <p>But to come more ſpecially to a review of the great Charge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the damages between Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> he chargeth him with robbing of him of 24 or 2500 <hi>l.</hi> which you ſee is every word of it falſe, with endeavouring to take away his life, which you ſee is a lye: But what recompence may Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> demand? nay, what recompence can <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> give to him, and the other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (conſidering the diſproportion of the perſons,) who hath endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſtretch the utmoſt limits of malice, to blaſt their reputations, and take their good names from them, which <hi>Solomon</hi> profeſſeth in <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.1. <hi>is better, and rather to be choſen then great riches?</hi> What is rob'd and ſtoln from me, may be made up again ſeven-fold; but my name, that, is like a glaſs, that holds ſome precious liquor, once broken, can hardly ever be made up again in that beauty and firmneſs as it was before: A good name it's the perfume of noble ſpirits and actions, without which men ſtink as they walk in the world, and is the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this world of vertue and proweſs, by this men live when they dye, and are famous to eternity. What a <hi>Cannibal</hi> is this <hi>Lilburn</hi> then? And what a ravenous ſpirit hath he, that nothing but the ruine of the honour and good names of the moſt deſerving men can content his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice? What is <hi>Lilburns</hi> 24 or 2500 <hi>l.</hi> to make up ſuch a breach? But the man is ſenſible of no diſhonour himſelf, his perſon or fortunes being never yet capable of any.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> were ſo ſenſible of the names of the Citizens or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they made ſpecial Laws, with moſt ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, againſt Libellers, or any that ſhould write Pamphlets to defame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165445:11"/> any Free-man, or take away his good report, <hi>Cicero lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de repub: flagitium capital eſto,</hi> Let it be a capital offence, that is as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <hi>quod capitis poena luitur,</hi> which ſhall endanger a mans head, but publikely to defame any man, without legal conviction.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>paudectis ex ulpiano,</hi> he that ſhall write to defame and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize a Citizen, whether without name, or in the name of another, or by his own name, <hi>Inteſtabilis ex lege eſſe jubetur,</hi> that was the character the Law gave him, (that is) <hi>qui nec teſtamentum facere potest, nec ad teſtimonium adheberi teſtis,</hi> was never to be beleeved more in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſaid, nor his teſtimony ever more to be credited: And <hi>Horace</hi> obſerving the ſame Law and Sentence, <hi>Intestabilis dixit pro deteſtabili,</hi> a man deteſtible, and to be abominated by all men of any honeſty or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity; and that the world may further ſee the hainouſneſs of this Crime, the <hi>Graecians</hi> (as <hi>Budeus</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Commentaries</hi>) were wont to call the ſame men (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>velut fortunis omnibus averſi, civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia jura non retinebant,</hi> men forſaken of all fortunes, that keep to no civil Rule or Law, as baniſhed, and diſſolute men, that enjoy nothing, and care to live by no rule but their luſt, <hi>preſidii legum exortes,</hi> out of protection of Law and Juſtice, and yet he gives a further deſcription in the ſame place of thoſe men, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>dicti fuerunt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men of diſhonour, that act wickedly, and talk wickedly, to whom no reſpect, nor eſteem is to be given on any terms. You ſee how libelling was reſented among the wiſeſt and beſt governed <hi>States</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms;</hi> and doubtleſs the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are not defective, as to this offence. Murther and ſlander ſeem of a like hainous nature; yea, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to an ingenious and raiſed ſpirit, ſeems the greater miſery; many would rather chooſe to dye, then to live baſely: Murther to an honeſt man, is rather the ſin of the murtherer, then the hurt of the perſon, he being better provided for; but ſlander kills the man, while he lives, and without any hope of reparation; the death it ſelf of the libeller cannot make up the loſs, for when he is gone, the man that lives under that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, ſuffers a dayly Martyrdom, and lives as a forlorn and dead man, without love or reſpect, <hi>telluris inutile pondus,</hi> as the burthen and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of the earth.</p>
            <p>What a ſentence then of Condemnation would be paſt on this man, if he had his due? How will his name rot to poſterity, who hath ſo unchriſtianlike and unworthily ſlandered theſe two Gentlemen? As I dare ſay, never any were by the moſt horrid and wretched tongue in the world, yea the very language of <hi>Bedlam</hi> and <hi>Billingſgate</hi> is ſmooth and comely to his expreſſions.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:165445:12"/>
            <p>But I cannot wonder that his rage is ſo much againſt them, ſeeing the very <hi>Churches of Chriſt</hi> (thoſe ſacred Bodies and Pillars of Glory) are the butt of his fury, calling Mr <hi>John Goodwins Congregation, A knaviſh Conspiracy:</hi> and in other Pamphlets doing the like to other Churches: What will this man come unto? Where will his malice centre? Will it not at laſt end in trampling on the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and the <hi>Name of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who doubtleſs ſtands in diametrical oppoſition to his ſpirit and actions.</p>
            <p>And that he may prove himſelf to be a perfect <hi>Iſhmaelite,</hi> to have his hand againſt every man, and ſatisfie his envy at once, he ſlanders the whole <hi>Parliament, Councel of State, Army,</hi> calling them <hi>Col: Prides Iunto, a mock Parliament, a company of Theeves, Robbers,</hi> with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſuch like <hi>Monſters,</hi> and, which is intolerable, glories in this his ſhame; never was any <hi>State</hi> ſo publikely affronted by ſuch a <hi>pedantique Pamphleter,</hi> and yet ſo patient and indulgent to him; yet though he denies their Authority, and profeſſeth contempt againſt them, as no <hi>Parliament,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> upon <hi>an Agreement of the People</hi> (that grant Idol of the <hi>Levellers</hi>) though it were but of the thouſand part of them, and conſiſting only of a few <hi>Apprentices,</hi> and <hi>Bankrupts,</hi> and men of inconſiderable intereſt in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> could be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not only to purge but diſſolve this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and chooſe whom they pleaſed, and have put the ſtamp of <hi>the Supream Authority of this Nation</hi> on it. It's well known, that there are far more of all ſorts that have heartily and freely conſented to this preſent <hi>Authority,</hi> then ever would have done on ſuch an <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> (according to his model,) in which there was ſuch <hi>Popular Principles,</hi> ſuch a looſe and <hi>licentious Liberty,</hi> to be given to all ſorts of wicked <hi>Blasphemies</hi> and <hi>Opinions,</hi> that all godly and conſciencious men abominate; if the Army would have agreed with him, and two or three more <hi>Mechanick Levellers,</hi> though neither <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> nor <hi>Independent,</hi> neither one party nor other, but themſelves had conſented to it, they would have (if they had power) ſubjected all mens judgments and conſciences to it, and have cry'd it up for <hi>the firſt Parliament of Freedom &amp; Liberty that ever England enjoyed:</hi> And had that party prevailed againſt the Army, which mutinied of late, and gathered a Head at <hi>Burford</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> we ſhould have ſoon ſeen what a <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Councel of State</hi> we ſhould have been bleſſed with: And this very <hi>Parliament,</hi> in its illegal eſtate, yea, the <hi>Councel of State</hi> it ſelf, if it had but <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burns</hi> hands layd on it, ſhould be the <hi>Supream Authority</hi> in a moment. But what need all this ſpending of paper and words on him, who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165445:12"/> to dy a royal death with the King, and end his days like a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant,</hi> denying the <hi>authority</hi> of theſe, who found a <hi>juſt power</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning him. The <hi>Government</hi> is now happily changed, both by the Principles of <hi>Reaſon, Neceſſity, and Conveniency:</hi> If guilty perſons hate the Authority by which they muſt be condemned, I ſhall not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: For <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> I know his nature is onely diſpoſed to oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and no Government whatever ſhall be appointed, without that wherein he might be Supream, but he would cry it down as <hi>illegal and tyrannical.</hi> But if he thinks to dye a Martyr, in oppoſing this preſent <hi>Government,</hi> I ſhall not envy him the glory to be canoniz'd with King <hi>Charls</hi> in the <hi>Malignant and Popiſh Kalender.</hi> I ſhall ſay no more as to this, but leave him to the righteous execution of their Power, whom he denies to have Authority.</p>
            <p>And whereas he ſtill pleads to be tryed by the <hi>known Laws of the Land,</hi> you may ſee he is put to his ſhifts; when he fought againſt the King, he could finde a diſtinction between the ſence of the Law, and intent of it, and the letter; and now he is come to be tryed by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he flies to the letter of theſe Laws, by which he could not, without Treaſon, fight againſt the King; but any thing to ſcape the Gallows: Had he ſtood to every Statute Law formerly, where had <hi>John Lilburn</hi> been? Nay, did not <hi>John Lilburn</hi> juſtly deſerve all thoſe whips and ſcourges, by the letter of ſome Laws then in force? Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Laws are made according to particular occaſions &amp; conveniencies, and bind not <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> eſpecially no occaſional Statutes can binde up the hands of the Legiſlators; the <hi>Parliament</hi> being the <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the People,</hi> are the <hi>Supream Authority,</hi> and what they enact, or do, in the time of their <hi>Seſſion,</hi> is to be accounted as abſolute a Law (at leaſt as long as they ſhall think fit to continue it) as any other Law made by former Parliaments; and to tye the <hi>Supream Authority</hi> to former preſidents, is all one as to give Laws to the <hi>Legiſlators.</hi> And whereas <hi>John Lilburn</hi> will have the <hi>Parliament,</hi> both now, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, to follow the form of every common <hi>Statute</hi> in making an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for his impriſonment, it is as much as to ſay, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath not power to repeal, or, as they ſee occaſion, to ſuſpend the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, or alter the form of any <hi>Statute;</hi> or that their Orders, in the time of their <hi>Seſſion,</hi> though but occaſionally made, and <hi>pro tempore,</hi> according as they ſee neceſſity or conveniency, are not as legal and juſt, and to be obeyed, as theſe <hi>Statutes</hi> which other <hi>Parliaments</hi> made on the ſight of the ſame convenience, or reaſon: But there is no doubt but they have Laws enough to prove <hi>John Lilburn</hi> a Traytor, and a man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165445:13"/> which deſerves the laſt puniſhment; But if there ſhould be a defect of any expreſs Preſident, or Law, whereby he may be puniſhed, it's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath gone beyond the common ſtrain of former offendors, and is without preſident and example in his miſcarriages; and no <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> could ever imagine, there would any man be ſo quite deſtitute of the Law of Nature, as to abuſe himſelf, and affront Authority ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently, as he hath done; But new ſins muſt have new puniſhments: Some muſt be made examples now, as well as others formerly. It was the Earl of <hi>Straffords</hi> plea, there was no Law and preſident for his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, who acted it better then <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and yet <hi>Iohn</hi> was one of the Apprentices that cried out for Juſtice, which was legally executed then; And the King denyed the Authority of the <hi>High Court of Iuſtice,</hi> and yet juſtly loſt his Head: Let <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> take heed next, The <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> hath made a Law, and it's publiſhed, <hi>That who ever ſhall ſpeak againſt the preſent Government, or for the title of Prince</hi> Charls <hi>to the Crown, ſhall be puniſhed as a Traytor;</hi> How far the Gentleman hath ſin'd againſt this known Law, he may ſhortly know.</p>
            <p>I have now done with his terrible and hyperbolical Charges, though it ſeems he means never to have done, for he ſtiles his laſt Pamphlet but <hi>A Preparative to a Hue and Cry,</hi> and in the latter end of his <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> calls for more fuel to the fire, commanding his Uncle (as if he were the god of this world) to ſend up to him intelligence what Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> doth, and <hi>Let me know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if he do not this, and that, profeſſing he will not abate him an ace, be it true or falſe, which he can but ſcrape out of any Malignant Letters concerning him;</hi> But I hope by this time all ſober and honeſt men know what uſe to put his Pamphlets unto hereafter: And to thoſe that have a minde to buy a ſhillingworth of lyes to carry in their pockets againſt they ſhall finde uſe of them, or would learn the art of railing and ſlandering moſt exactly, I ſhall commend the buying of Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburns</hi> Pamphlets, and reading of them with the moſt care and diligence that they can afford; For my part, my ſtomack is full, I ſhall onely deſire theſe two Gentlemen, that are thus the objects of his revenge, That though your Names and Honors are untainted, and ſhine clear through the cloud of his Calumnies, yet you would make this advantage of it, and ſo honeſtly cheat him of his hopes, to ſpur you on to more gallant and brave actions, and to improve your Intereſt for the advancing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Power of Godlineſs in this Nation, as well as Civil Freedom and Liberty, then ſhall your names be written in Braſs or Marble, to poſterity, as they are, and will be, in the hearts of godly and conſciencious men, when <hi>John Lilburns</hi> ſhall be written in the duſt.</p>
            <p>I expect another <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> after me ſhortly; But I intend to foul my hands no more with him; but leave the diſcreet Reader to judg, and beſtow what Faith and Charity he hath to ſpare upon his former and enſuing Pamphlets.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
